Kathleen T Quach

San Diego, CA

Summary.

A **behavioral neuroscientist** with ten years of independent research experience, specializing in the application of ethological, neuroeconomic, and other behavioral frameworks to analyze decision-making processes of both predator and prey in naturalistic predator-prey interactions in a laboratory setting.

Education

University of California, San Diego (UCSD)

La Jolla, CA, USA

PhD in Neurosciences, Specialization in Computational Neuroscience

2019

• GPA: 3.734 / 4.000

University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA)

Los Angeles, CA, USA

BS in Neuroscience

2010

• GPA: 3.618 / 4.000

Research Experience_

Salk Institute for Biological Studies (Molecular Neurobiology, PI: Sreekanth Chalasani)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Postdoctoral Fellow

2019.09 - 2024.04

- Led projects investigating the decision-making and molecular regulation of defensive behaviors by *Caenorhabditis elegans* nematodes in response to *Pristionchus pacificus* predators.
- Integrated concepts from predatory imminence theory and prey refuge theory to build a behavioral framework that can be used to predict, elicit, and interpret *Caenorhabditis elegans* defensive behaviors in response to changes in various dimensions of perceived predation risk.
- Conducted behavioral experiments on genetic mutants and transgenic strains to identify changes in interdependence between signaling partners across stages of defensive behaviors.

Salk Institute for Biological Studies (Molecular Neurobiology, PI: Sreekanth Chalasani)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Graduate Student

2012.07 - 2019.09

- Led projects investigating the decision-making and molecular regulation of foraging decisions by *Pristionchus pacificus* predatory nematodes in response to predator-prey competition with *Caenorhabditis elegans* prey nematodes.
- Integrated concepts from foraging theory, neuroeconomic theory, and intraguild predation theory to build a behavioral framework that can be used to predict, elicit, and distinguish between predatory and territorial motivations for attacking *Caenorhabditis elegans*.
- Conducted a screen of pharmacologically active compounds to identify signaling mechanisms underlying the switch between predatory and territorial motivation, using the behavioral framework to directly target decision-making processes rather than motor or sensory processes.
- Other projects: Co-led a project investigating whole-brain activity of *Caenorhabditis elegans* nematodes to understand how state-dependent network interactions gate sensory input at the motor and command neuron level. Supported a project investigating neural regulation of hypoxia reponses in *Danio rerio* zebrafish.

UCLA (Psychiatry and Biobehavioral Sciences, PI: Mirella Dapretto)

Los Angeles, CA, USA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2009.02 - 2010.06

- Conducted independent research investigating abnormal effective connectivity during emotional face processing in children with autism spectrum disorders.
- Applied dynamic causal modeling to fMRI time series data to estimate directionality and strength of coupling between brain regions during viewing
 of emotional faces.
- Developed methods for automating data entry of survey inputs from test subjects.

UCLA (Neurology, PI: Jack Van Horn)

Los Angeles, CA, USA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2010.01 - 2010.06

• Designed graphical user interface elements for Invizian neuroinformatics software.

UCLA (Psychiatry and Biobehavioral Sciences, PI: Susan Bookheimer)

Los Angeles, CA, USA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2009.03 - 2010.06

- Scored eye gaze behavior of 36-month old infants with autism spectrum disorders and their siblings during social interaction with caregivers and strangers.
- Drew regions of interests to quantify how much time is spent looking at facial, body, and background features.
- Developed code for automated parsing of Tobii software output.

APRIL 30, 2024

Undergraduate Research and Therapist Assistant

2007.06 - 2009.09

- · Assisted in cognitive behavioral therapy for treatment of anxiety in children with autism spectrum disorders.
- · Performed data entry of therapy intake assessments and patient questionnaires for analysis in SPSS.

Industry Experience

Starbucks Coffee Company

Seattle, WA, USA

Implementation Specialist

2011.12 - 2012.06

 Analyzed data and implemented strategies for optimizing the function of retail networks and public Wi-Fi in over 10,000 Starbucks stores across North America.

Teaching and Outreach Experience

Salk Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship (SURF)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Application Reviewer

2023.11 - 2023.12

• Reviewed anonymized applications based on a rubric that assessed need and career goals.

Salk Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship (SURF)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Developer & Presenter

2023.06.12

• Developed and presented a workshop (*Thinking like a Scientist*), introducing undergraduate interns to the values and philosophy guiding scientific research, and the principles of fostering a scientific personality resilient to failures and biases.

Salk Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship (SURF)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Mentor

2022.05 - 2022.08, 2023.05 - 2023.08

• Intensively mentored undergraduates from under-resourced institutions to perform independent research in a 10-week program.

UCSD Biology Undergraduate and Master's Mentorship Program (BUUMP)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Mentor

2020.09 - 2021.02

• Mentored biology undergraduate students from underrepresented minorities.

UCSD Graduate Division (Course: Fundamentals of Statistics and Computation for Neuroscientists)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Course Developer & Instructor

2016.03 - 2016.06

• Developed and taught a graduate-level introductory course designed to provide literacy in and exposure to computational techniques.

UCSD Graduate Division (Course: Introduction to Methods in Computational Neuroscience, Instructor: Pam Reinegal)

La Jolla, CA, USA

Teaching Assistant

2015.09 - 2015.12

Assisted in teaching a graduate-level course on mathematical foundations and applications of computational neuroscience methods.

Monarch School San Diego, CA, USA

Tutor

2022.09 - 2022.11

· Tutored chemistry to students impacted by homelessness to compensate for shortage of science teachers.

Publications

Quach, K. T.*, Hughes, G. A., & Chalasani, S. H. (2024). Interdependence between SEB-3 and NLP-49 peptides shifts across predator-induced defensive behavioral modes in *Caenorhabditis elegans*. Submitted to *eLife*.

Quach, K. T., & Chalasani, S. H. (2022). Flexible reprogramming of *Pristionchus pacificus* motivation for attacking *Caenorhabditis elegans* in predator-prey competition. *Current Biology*, 32(8), 1675-1688.

Cecere, Z. T.*, Quach, K. T.*, Yemini, E., How, J. J., Sharpee, T. O., & Chalasani, S. H. (2021). State-dependent network interactions differentially gate sensory input at the motor and command neuron level in *Caenorhabditis elegans*. bioRxiv, 2021-04. *co-first authors

Quach, K. T., & Chalasani, S. H. (2020). Intraguild predation between *Pristionchus pacificus* and *Caenorhabditis elegans*: a complex interaction with the potential for aggressive behaviour. *Journal of neurogenetics*, 34(3-4), 404-419.

Abstracts and .pdf versions are available at kathleenqua.ch/publications.

APRIL 30, 2024 2

Awards

2022.12 - 2024.11	Maximillian E. and Marion O. Hoffman Foundation Award
2020.06 - 2022.06	Paul F. Glenn Center for Biology of Aging Research Fellow
2018.07 - 2019.07	Salk Women and Science Award
2018.03 - 2019.03	Mary K. Chapman Foundation Award
2018.10 - 2018.03	Jesse and Caryl Philips Foundation Award
2016.05.21	Neurosciences Graduate Teaching Award
2014.09 - 2017.08	National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellow

Laboratory Skills

Model Organisms Caenorhabditis elegans (nematode), Pristionchus pacificus (nematode), Danio rerio (zebrafish), human

Behavior predator-prey interaction, foraging, chemotaxis, adaptation, exploration, egg-laying

Microscopy brightfield/DIC/fluorescence, light/confocal, laser microsurgery, calcium imaging, expansion

Staining immunocytochemistry, Dil/DiO (neuronal tracer), Oil Red O (fat)

Pharmacology drug screens using LOPAC 1280, neurotransmitters and associated agonists/antagonists, paralytics

Bacteria culturing/incubation, streaking/spreading/plating, colony counting, spectrophotometry, transformation, antibiotic selection

Microfluidics device fabrication, device operation, automated control of laminar flows

Molecular biology cloning, DNA/RNA purification, PCR, primer design, gel electrophoresis, DNA/RNAseq, DNA/RNA quantity/quality assessment

Computational Methods _____

Theories & Frameworks foraging theory, expected utility theory, intraguild predation theory, predatory imminence theory, prey refuge theory,

information theory

Statistics tests for nominal variables, parametric/non-parametric tests for one/multiple measurement variable(s), ANCOVA,

linear/nonlinear correlation, linear/logistic regression models, linear mixed-effects models, bootstrapping, data

transformation, distributional analysis, power analysis, machine-learning

Image Processing image segmentation, image deconvolution, morphological processing, fluorescence intensity quantification, color

deconvolution

Neural Dynamics time series analysis, dimensionality reduction, network analysis, network modeling

Software, Platforms, & Languages _____

Scientific Computing MATLAB, R

Image Acquisition and Processing ImageJ, Zen, Streampix, Metamorph

Bioinformatics APE, Geneious, BLAST, Primer-BLAST, Galaxy, UCSD Genome Browser, IGV

OS Windows, Linux (Ubuntu)

Adobe Acrobat, Illustrator, Photoshop, InDesign

Microsoft Office Word, Excel, OneNote

Google Drive, Docs, Sheets, Slides, Forms

Collaboration Zoom, Slack

Electronic Lab Notebook Benchling

Command Line BASH, Powershell

Web HTML, Markdown, CSS

Typesetting LaTeX, Overleaf, TeXmaker

Version Control Git, Github
Container Docker

IDE Visual Studio

Data Serialization Formats JSON, YAML

Diagramming PlantUML

APRIL 30, 2024 3